A Guide to the Roller Family Papers 1828-1974
Virginia Historical Society
Virginia Historical Society
Roller Family Papers 1828-1974
Virginia Historical Society
Mss1R6498bFA2
This collection consists of ca. 3.400 items, held in 33 manuscript boxes.
Includes correspondence, account books and loose accounts, commonplace books, and miscellaneous materials documenting the close relationship between members of the Cabell and the related Micklem and Eubank families, especially among the women. Prominently represented are Elizabeth Willis (Eubank) Cabell of "Inglewood," Nelson County, Va., who maintained a large household made up of her immediate family, her husband's sister, children who attended the school run by her son and daughter, and summer boarders; and her daughters, Mary Caroline Cabell, a teacher who ran the school at Inglewood; Lucy Brown (Cabell) Roller, who married John Edwin Roller of Harrisonburg, Va., and had an active domestic and social life; and Margaret Etta (Cabell) Matthews, who married an Anglican missionary and lived with him for several years in Liberia; and Elizabeth Henry (Roller) Bottimore, of Richmond, Va., and Glens Falls, N.Y., daughter of Lucy Brown (Cabell) Roller, who maintained an extensive social correspondence with friends, many of whom lived in or frequently travelled to foreign countries. In general the correspondence concerns domestic activities, including courtship and marriage, the births of children, illnesses and deaths, problems with servants, and the procurement of clothing and other household articles; the running of the Inglewood school and the work of other family members, split between teaching and the law; and social activities in Nelson County, Harrisonburg, and Richmond, Va., among the Cabell and Roller families and a wide network of friends and relations. Also included are the papers of John Edwin Roller, a Harrisonburg, Va., lawyer and active member of the Republican Party, largely concerning his plans to run for the Virginia House of Delegates in 1872 and his relationships with his wife, her daughters, and his daughters from his first marriage.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Roller Family Papers were received by the Virginia Historical Society in 1989 as the gift of Mrs. Elizabeth Henry (Roller) Bottimore. They were accessioned 25 September 1995.
Biographical/Historical Information
Records of three generations of the Cabell family of "Inglewood," Variety Mills, Nelson co., Va., and two generations of the Roller family of Harrisonburg, Va.
Represented are George Washington Cabell (1802-1869), farmer and planter, and his wife, Mary Anne (Anthony) Cabell (1808-1868), daughter of Christopher Anthony, Jr. (1776-1835), attorney of Lynchburg, Va.; their son-in-law, Joseph Laidley (1829-1861); their daughter, Lucy Brown Cabell (1836-1911), called "Lucie," who never married; their son, Patrick Henry Cabell (1837-1907), called "Pat," professor at Lynchburg Military College, Superintendent of Schools for Nelson co., and employee of Southern Railway; Patrick Henry Cabell's wife, Elizabeth Willis Eubank (1843-1907), called "Bettie," daughter of Royal H. Eubank of Nelson co., Va.; and their children, Patrick Henry "Carey" Cabell (1864-1920), of Richmond, Va., lawyer and representative of the Travelers Insurance Company; Mary Caroline Cabell (1866-1942), called "Callie," a Hollins Institute graduate who ran a school at the family home, "Inglewood"; Anne Woolston (Cabell) Flowers (1869-1958), graduate of the State Female Normal School at Farmville, Va. [now Longwood College], who married Charles H. Flowers of Vandemere, N.C.; Lucy Brown (Cabell) Roller (1871-1914), called "Lily," teacher, who married John Edwin Roller of Harrisonburg, Va.; George Washington Cabell (1873-1943), of "Inglewood," Nelson co., Va., farmer and justice of the peace, graduate of the Virginia Military Institute who later studied law at the University of Virginia and ran, with his sister, Mary Caroline Cabell, the Inglewood school; Margaret "Etta" (Cabell) Matthews (1876-1969), who attended the State Female Normal School at Farmville, Va. [now Longwood College], and taught at schools in western Virginia, married the Rev. Nathan Matthews, Anglican missionary and priest from Newfoundland and lived with him in Liberia, South Carolina, Tennessee and Massachusetts; Royal Eubank Cabell (1878-1950), who attended Roanoke College, Salem, Va., Princeton University, the University of Virginia, and Richmond College (now the University of Richmond), lawyer of Richmond, Va., later U.S. Postmaster of Richmond, 1906-1909, and Commissioner of Internal Revenue under President Theodore Roosevelt before returning to Richmond to resume his law practice; and Somers Eubank Cabell (1885-1919), who studied electrical engineering at Virginia Polytechnic Institute at Blacksburg, Va., and later worked for General Electric and the Virginia Iron, Coal and Coke Company.
Also represented are Lucy Brown (Cabell) Roller's husband, John Edwin Roller (1844-1918), prominent lawyer of Harrisonburg, Va., Confederate veteran, instructor at the Virginia Military Institute, which he attended, and active member of the Republican Party; his daughters by his first marriage, Frances Lewis (Roller) Grattan, called "Lewie," of Harrisonburg, Va., and Margaret Stuart (Roller) Cannady Ogilvie Merryman, called "Marco," of Harrisonburg, Va., and W. Va.; and his daughters with Lucy Brown Cabell, "Lucy Cabell" Roller (1899-1949) of Harrisonburg and Richmond, Va., who attended Randolph-Macon Women's College and Columbia University; Elizabeth Henry (Roller) Bottimore (1902-1993) of Harrisonburg and Richmond, Va., who attended Chatham Hall, Randolph-Macon Women's College, and Wellesley College, and married William Gordon Bottimore of Richmond and Glens Falls, N.Y.; and Anne Woolston (Roller) Pyle (1904-1977) of Richmond, Va., who attended Chatham Hall and Wellesley College and married Wilfred Pyle (b. ca. 1907), son of artist Howard Pyle.
Also included are scattered letters of the Micklem, Eubank, Calwell, and related families.
Scope and Content Information
Chiefly the papers of Elizabeth Willis (Eubank) Cabell, her daughters Mary Caroline Cabell and Lucy Brown (Cabell) Roller, Lucy's husband, John Edwin Roller, and Lucy and John's daughter, Elizabeth Henry (Roller) Bottimore, consisting primarily of correspondence among the various members of the Cabell family.
Elizabeth Willis (Eubank) Cabell's correspondence with her nine children documents their attendance at various Virginia universities, their work as lawyers, teachers, and engineers, their marriages and the births of their children, and her domestic activities running the large household at Inglewood and the taking of summer boarders.
Papers of Mary Caroline Cabell include correspondence with her siblings concerning the activities of various family members, social events in Nelson County, and the running of the Inglewood school.
Papers of Lucy Brown (Cabell) Roller include correspondence with female family members and friends concerning her marriage, the births of her daughters, the activities of her Cabell relatives, and her involvement with several patriotic societies.
Papers of John Edwin Roller consist primarily of correspondence concerning his plans to run for election to the Virginia House of Delegates in 1872, and, after his marriage in 1896, the well-being of his wife and daughters, especially the activities of daughters Frances and Margaret while attending the Woman's College, Frederick, Md. [now Hood College], and Virginia Female Institute, Staunton, Va.
Papers of Elizabeth Henry (Roller) Bottimore consist mainly of correspondence with aging Cabell and Roller relations and with friends in America and abroad while she lived in Glens Falls, N.Y., and concern her social life and family news.
Organization
The papers of the Cabell and Roller families are arranged into series as follows:
Series 1.
George Washington Cabell (1802-1869) account book, 1833-1839.
Series 2.
Mary Anne (Anthony) Cabell (1808-1868) commonplace book, 1828-1834.
Series 3.
Joseph Laidley (1829-1861) diary, 1853.
Series 4.
Lucy Brown Cabell (1836-1911) papers, including correspondence, 1854-1906; accounts, 1882-1893; commonplace book, 1849-1859; materials concerning Margaret Clifford Cabell (1835-1888), 1887-1888; and miscellaneous materials, 1852-1888.
Series 5.
Patrick Henry Cabell (1837-1907) papers, including correspondence, 1859-1906; accounts, 1898-1899; school materials, including school exercise books, 1854- 1858, commonplace book, 1858-1859, and class notes, 1858; and invitations, 1899-1906.
Series 6.
Elizabeth Willis (Eubank) Cabell (1843-1907) papers, including correspondence, 1897-1907; accounts; and miscellaneous materials.
Series 7.
Patrick Henry Carey Cabell (1864-1920) papers, including correspondence, 1896-1920; issues, 1877, of the Amateur Press, published in Monte Vista and Montreal, Va.; and miscellaneous materials.
Series 8.
Mary Caroline Cabell (1866-1942) papers, including correspondence, 1899-1940; financial materials, 1931-1932; school materials, 1853-1932; scrapbook; and miscellaneous materials.
Series 9.
Anne Woolston (Cabell) Flowers (1869-1958) correspondence, 1890-1951.
Series 10.
John Edwin Roller (1844-1918) papers, including correspondence, 1870-1916; financial materials, 1894-1918; historical manuscripts; school materials; and miscellaneous materials.
Series 11.
Lucy Brown (Cabell) Roller (1871-1914) papers, including correspondence, 1888-1914; accounts, 1896-1912; materials concerning the Colonial Dames of America in the State of Virginia; materials concerning the Daughters of the American Revolution, Massanutten Chapter; invitations; visiting cards; and miscellaneous materials.
Series 12.
George Washington Cabell (1873-1943) papers, including correspondence, 1899-1920; and accounts, 1911-1914.
Series 13.
Margaret Etta (Cabell) Matthews (1876-1969) papers, including correspondence, 1888-1954; and miscellaneous materials.
Series 14.
Royal Eubank Cabell (1878-1950) correspondence, 1897-1912.
Series 15.
Somers Eubank Cabell (1885-1919) school materials, 1903-1904.
Series 16.
Frances Lewis (Roller) Grattan correspondence, 1897-1959.
Series 17.
Margaret Stuart (Roller) Cannady Ogilvie Merryman correspondence, 1899-1947; and school materials, 1897-1898.
Series 18.
Lucy Cabell Roller (1899-1949) correspondence, 1899-1947.
Series 19.
Elizabeth Henry (Roller) Bottimore (1902-1993) papers, including correspondence, 1927-1960; financial materials, 1955; certificates; commonplace books, 1942 and n.d.; invitations; and miscellaneous materials.
Series 20.
Anne Woolston (Roller) Pyle (1904-1977) correspondence, 1912-1959.
Series 21.
Miscellaneous Cabell, Micklem, and Roller family correspondence, 1872-1907.
Contents List
- George Washington Cabell (1802-1869) account book 1833-1839, 1 v. (Box 1)
  Kept at "Inglewood," Nelson co., Va. Concerns farming operations and lumber trade. Includes short stories written by Lucy Brown Cabell (1836-1911).
- Mary Anne (Anthony) Cabell (1808-1868) commonplace book 1828-1834, 1 v. (Box 1)
  Kept at "Inglewood," Nelson co., Va. Includes essays and lines of verse, chiefly on religious topics.
- Joseph Laidley (1829-1861) diary 1853 August 12-28, 1v. (Box 1)
  Kept in Richmond, Va., at Huguenot Springs, Powhatan co., Va., and on a railroad trip from Richmond to Boston, Mass. Concerns activities as an officer of the American Pharmaceutical Association. Also, includes lists of members of the American Pharmaceutical Association, notes, and accounts.
- Lucy Brown Cabell (1836-1911) papers
  - Correspondence, 1854-1906 (66 items)., 66 items (Box 1)
    Include letters of Delphia Boudreaux (while serving with the Bienville Guards, Company C, 5th Louisiana Infantry Regiment, C.S.A., concerning the Chancellorsville Campaign, 1863), niece Anne Woolston (Cabell) Flowers (while away from home, teaching at Timberville, Va., Scotland, Ky., and Vandemere, N.C., concerning social life in Nelson co. and family news), William Henry Kinckle (concerning religious dedication), and niece Lucy Brown (Cabell) Roller (after her marriage and removal to Harrisonburg, Va., concerning home life in both Nelson co. and Harrisonburg).
    Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
    Correspondents include:
    Albin, Edgar W.
    Boudreaux, Delphia
    Burkhardt, Jane Carr (Dunn)
    Cabell, George Washington
    Cabell, Patrick Henry Carey
    Cabell, Richard Hawes
    Cabell, Sallie J. Laidley
    Cabell, Samuel Jordan
    Early, Ruth Hairston
    Eubank, Willis Milton
    Flowers, Annie Woolston (Cabell)
    Kinckle, William Henry
    Matthews, Margaret Etta (Cabell)
    Miles, Lavinia
    Roller, Lucy Brown (Cabell)
    Roller, Lucy Cabell
  - Accounts: check stub book 1882-1893; 1887-1890, 5 items (Box 1)
    Concerns the account of Lucy Brown Cabell in the National Exchange Bank of Lynchburg, Va.
  - Commonplace book, 1849-1859, 1 v. (Box 2)
    Kept at "Inglewood," Nelson co., Va. Include lines of verse.
  - Materials relating to Margaret Clifford Cabell (1835-1888) 1887-1888, 14 items (Box 2)
    Materials relate to Margaret C. Cabell, while an inmate at the Western Lunatic Asylum (now Western State Hospital), Staunton, Va.
    Include correspondence with C. J. Armistead, Margaret Clifford Cabell, Doctor Daniel Burr Conrad, Doctor Edward Carrington Fisher, Lizzie W. LeNeve, and George S. Walker.
  - Miscellaneous materials, 1852-1888, 40 items (Box 2)
    Include obituary notices of George Washington Cabell (1802-1869), Mary Anne (Anthony) Cabell (1808-1868), William Washington Cabell, Sarah Syme (Cabell) Laidley (1830-1862), Mrs. Sallie Morris, Harriet W. Steptoe, and Sarah Armistead (Garland) Waller; visiting cards of Lucy Brown Cabell and Sarah Syme (Cabell) Laidley; materials concerning the Louisiana State Lottery; recipes; and lines of verse.
- Patrick Henry Cabell (1837-1907) papers.
  - Correspondence, 1859-1906, 75 items (Box 3)
    Correspondence of Patrick Henry Cabell of "Inglewood," Nelson co., Va., while serving as county superintendent of schools, and at Lynchburg, Va., while employed by the Southern Railway Company, chiefly with his wife, Elizabeth Willis (Eubank) Cabell, and daughters Lucy Brown (Cabell) Roller and Mary Caroline Cabell. Of particular interest is a letter, 1862, of Mary Anne (Anthony) Cabell written prior to her death listing possessions to be distributed among her children; and a letter to J. W. Henley enclosed in a letter of Patrick Henry Carey Cabell concerning mineral rights and copper mines at "Inglewood" and other properties in Nelson Co.
    Cabell, Elizabeth Willis (Eubank)
    Cabell, John Willis
    Cabell, Mary Anne (Anthony)
    Cabell, Mary Caroline
    Cabell, Royal Eubank
    Cabell, Somers Eubank
    Cooley, Benjamin F.
    Flowers, Charles H.
    Hamilton, Robert S.
    Henley, J. W. See Cabell, Patrick Henry Carey
    Hoy, David L. See Cabell, Royal Eubank
    Roller, John Edwin
    Ruffner, William Henry
    Southern Railway Company
    Virginia State Board of Education
  - Accounts, 1898-1899, 6 items (Box 3)
    Kept in Lynchburg, Va.
  - School materials, 1854-1858, 5 v. plus 4 loose items (Box 3)
    Include notebooks and Latin and Greek exercise books, 1854-1858, kept as a student at Emory and Henry College, Emory, Va., and while teaching at Lynchburg College, Lynchburg, Va.; commonplace book, 1858-1859, kept while teaching at Lynchburg College; and notes, 1858, concerning graduates of Emory and Henry College and classes at Lynchburg College.
  - Invitations, 1899-1906, 8 items (Box 3)
    Invitations to attend weddings and commencement ceremonies at the Episcopal Theological Seminary, Alexandria, Va.
- Elizabeth Willis (Eubank) Cabell (1843-1907) papers.
  - Correspondence, 1897-1907, ca. 400 items (Box 4-6)
    Correspondence of Elizabeth Willis "Bettie" (Eubank) Cabell, of "Inglewood," Variety Mills, Nelson co., Va., chiefly with her children and female relatives. Most non-family correspondence are letters of condolence for the deaths of various family members or requests for summer board.
    Of particular interest are letters of John Willis Cabell while attending Roanoke College, Salem, Va., 1898-1900, and working on the construction of railroads in Kentucky and Tennessee, 1901-1907; Patrick Henry Carey Cabell of Richmond, Va., concerning his law practice, health, and family news; Royal Eubank Cabell while attending Princeton University and while in Richmond working as his brother Carey's law partner, often discussing his brother's health problems and business activities; Somers Eubank Cabell while attending Virginia Polytechnic Institute, Blacksburg, Va., 1902-1906, and working as an electrical engineer in Schnectedy, N.Y., 1907; Annie Woolston (Cabell) Flowers concerning her employment as a teacher in Vandemere, N.C., 1903-1905; the Lorraine family of Richmond, Va., concerning mutual friends and relations; Margaret Etta (Cabell) Matthews while teaching school in Farmville and Salem, Va., in the late 1890s, and after her marriage to Rev. Nathan Matthews and move to Liberia, 1905-1907, describing the mission school and local customs; and Lucy Brown (Cabell) Roller discussing her adjustment as stepmother to her husbands' teenage daughters, the birth of her own children, and servant problems.
    Envelopes
    Unidentified
    Alexander, Margaret Anthony (Palmer)
    Ayres, Davis
    Ayres, Lina
    Barney, Rosa
    Bentley, Mary Grey
    Bentley, Virginia Lee
    Billups, L. A.
    Braisley, Arthur L.
    Brown, Sarah Randolph (Cabell)
    Cabell, Charles Ellet
    Cabell, Lillian Hoge (Lorraine)
    Cabell, Lucy Gilmer
    Cabell, Mary Holmes (McGuire)
    Cabell, Mary Virginia (Ellet)
    Cabell, Royal Eubank See also Cabell, Patrick Henry Carey
    Coleman, Frances Rutherfoord (Goodwin)
    Cutchins, Cary (Valentine)
    Darst, Thomas Campbell
    De Soucy, Pierre
    Dillard, S. C.
    Dunn, Annie Lewis
    Dunn, Elizabeth Irvine (Anthony) See: Roller, Lucy Brown (Cabell)
    Dunn, Susie Lamb (Hill)
    Early, Mary Washington (Cabell)
    Elsom, Anna Louise (Shepherd)
    Emerson, Jane P.
    Eubank, Elias Newman
    Eubank, Louise
    Eubank, Mollie M. (Purcell) See: Eubank, Otis A.
    Eubank, Otis A.
    Eubank, Sidney P.
    Fitzpatrick, J. F.
    Flowers, Anne Woolston (Cabell)
    Flowers, W. A.
    Ford, T. W. (Mrs.)
    Gardner, Alice Jane (Mosby)
    Gentry, John Edwin Roller
    Gillespie, Ellie
    Goode, Elvue
    Harris, L. W.
    Herrell, Hallie (Eubank)
    Higginbotham, Mary Ida (Day)
    Higginbotham, Mary Frances Coleman
    Holladay, Sallie Syme (Ayres)
    Hoofnagle, Lillie G. (Carrington)
    Hutson, Daisy H.
    Jamar, Annie Roberts
    Johnson, Eliza D.
    Johnson, Emma A.
    Lorraine, Emma Louise
    Lorraine, Martha Evelyn (Bohannon)
    Lorraine, Mary Eloise (Moore)
    Lorraine, Wellford Bohannon
    McCue, Lavinia M.
    McDunnough, Ethel Davison
    Mathews, Jessie Woods (Higginbotham)
    Meier, A. (Mrs.)
    Merryman, Margaret Stuart (Roller) Cannaday Ogilvie
    Micklem, Margaret Etta (Eubank)
    Moore, Cary Ann (Coleman)
    Morton, Blanche (McKay)
    Myers, Nellie L.
    Palmer, Alice Winston (Cabell)
    Pence, Mary Hagey (Wunder)
    Repass, Laeta Moore (Goodwin)
    Riggan, S. G.
    Saunders, O. Lee See: Roller, Lucy Brown (Cabell) (1905)
    Seddon, Elvira Bruce (Cabell)
    Sessoms, Virginia Constance (Quarles)
    Shipman, Sarah Louise (Johnson)
    Shipman, William Jordan
    Simpson, Emma B.
    Simpson, Mary Grace
    Skinner, Emma (Ayres)
    Taylor, George Braxton
    Tucker, Anna J.
    Valentine, Allen Wilson
    Valentine, Sally Cary (Finch)
    Whelan, Anna La Mott (McClelland)
    Wilson, Aggy P.
    Wilson, Edward F.
    Box 4: A-Cabell, Patrick Henry
    Box 5: Cabell, Royal Eubank - J
    Box 6: L - end
  - Accounts and miscellaneous materials 1901-1906 (Box 6)
    Including visiting cards, recipe, notes on health care, and lines of verse.
- Patrick Henry Carey Cabell (1864-1920) papers.
  - Correspondence, 1896-1920, 42 items (Box 7)
    Correspondence of Patrick Henry "Carey" Cabell, chiefly with his brothers and sisters. Letters, 1899-1907, to George Washington Cabell of Inglewood, Nelson co., Va., concern purchases of supplies for the farm and advice on farming and land transactions. Letters, 1897-1920[?], to Mary Caroline Cabell of Inglewood discuss family activities, Carey's health, and his engagements to Ethel Davison McDunnough of Montreal, Canada, in 1900 (later broken) and Mrs. Anne (Renfro) Tomlinson of Philadelphia, Pa., whom he married just months before his death in 1920. Letters, 1913-1918, to Mrs. Mary Hunter of Pendleton, Va., indicate the existence of a close friendship and mutual admiration. Letters, 1896-1912, to Lucy Brown (Cabell) Roller of Harrisonburg, Va., include a letter, 1899 May 31, announcing Carey's engagement to Ethel Davison McDunnough and giving information about her background, and a letter, 1900 March 16, enclosing a sketch by Carey of Samuel Jordan Cabell (1756-1818).
    Eichelberger, Harry D.
    Hunter, Mary (Mrs.)
    Talley, Robert H.
  - Amateur Press, Monte Vista and Montreal, Va., 1877 May - October, 9 items (Box 7)
    "A lively little journal edited and printed entirely by boys." Percy G. Elsom, editor; Patrick Henry Carey Cabell, associate editor.
  - Miscellaneous materials, 3 items (Box 7)
    Includes a bookplate, business card, and program for University of Virginia Public Day exercises, 1890 July 2, listing Patrick Henry Carey Cabell as receiving a Bachelor of Law degree.
- Mary Caroline Cabell (1866-1942) papers, 1853-1940
  - Correspondence, 1899-1940, ca. 600 items (Box 8-12)
    Correspondence of Mary Caroline "Callie" Cabell, primarily with female family members and friends. Many letters are condolences for the deaths of various family members, including Patrick Henry Cabell (1907), Elizabeth Willis (Eubank) Cabell (1907), Lucy Brown Cabell (1911), Somers Eubank Cabell (1919), Patrick Henry Carey Cabell (1920), and Ann Elizabeth (Moore) Cabell (1932). Also included are letters from the parents of students at the Inglewood school, chiefly concerning arrivals and departures and fees.